SIVAGAMI NATARAJAN(Ms.)
B2 103, Doshi First Nest, Thirumudivakkam,
Chennai, Tamil Nadu, India, 600044
sivagami.therapist@gmail.com
Mobile No +91 9047094094

#### **Professional Profile**

Social Worker with therapeutic skills and empowerment approach. Proven ability to work well with multidisciplinary teams. Experience in working with multi- ethnic, linguistics, national and religious teams. I would like to work with an organisation which takes social initiatives for the care, welfare, protection and rehabilitation of the vulnerable children and families.

# **Key Skills**

Ability to engage with people, Cultural competency, Strong interpersonal skills, Compassionate, Coordinating, Planing, Organising, Crisis intervention, Critical thinking, Documentation, Advocating, negotiating, Computer skills- Proficient user of Microsoft Office Tools.

#### Education

#### Institution / Qualification / Year

Madras School of Social work, Chennai, India / Master of Social work / 2010-2012
 India / Bachelor of Arts / 2001-2004

### Certifications

- Certified User of Child & Adolescent Needs & Strengths (CANS) 3,4,5 August 2015
- Mental Health First Aid 27, 28 May 2015
- Working with Children with Special Needs: Introduction to Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder - 30 May 2015
- Family and Adult Assessment Tool (FAST) 11 September 2016
- Working with Alcohol & Youth 14 November 2016
- Group Work Skills 16, 17 October 2017
- Management of Family Violence: Introduction 30, 31 October & 1 November 2017
- Management of Family Violence: Introduction to Child Abuse and Child Protection 26, 27 February 2018

#### Knowledge

• Strength's perspective intervention / • Multidimensional Assessment / • Evidence based Practice / • Behaviour Change Interventions / • Therapeutic Alliance / • Trauma informed case management / • Child development needs / • Psychosocial counselling

# **Employment History**

## Psychotherapist, Part-time, Spring Health, Chennai - December 2024 to Present

 Provide counseling to clients with benefits ranging from short-term goal-focused EAP, to employer health plans allowing as many sessions as medically necessary.

- Treat adults who have completed brief, evidence-based online screenings identifying their symptoms and areas of concern.
- Preferably, also be open to treating additional populations such as children, adolescents, couples, or families.

# Psychotherapist, Independent Practitioner - December 2019 to Present

• Counselling with children and families to address the behavioural concerns of children and the effective enhancement of the functioning of the family.

# State Program Manager - November 2018 – December 2019 Association for urban and rural needy (ARUN), Rainbow Homes Program, Chennai, India

- Work closely with the District Child Protection Unit, Child Welfare Committee to provide care and protection to the children from unsafe environments by placing them in the children's home for their holistic development.
- Lead to prepare Individual Care Plans for children in need of care and protection from unsafe and risky environments.
- Uplift families of Looking after children through attending to the children/young people's well-being and enhancing the caregiver's parenting capacity.
- Advocate for the rights of the children to grow to their maximum potential in safe environment in the government and civil platforms.

# Community Social Worker - September 2016 to July 2018 Thye Hua Kwan Moral Charities Limited, THKMC Bedok Family Service Centre, Singapore

- Provide intensive, home-based intervention and support to a caseload of families (high and medium intensity cases), and to ensure children's safety.
- Provide services that are inclusive of people from culturally and linguistically diverse backgrounds as well as engaging in learning about other cultures to better establish relationships and improve services.
- Identify the factors that impact upon family effectiveness in situations where child safety is a key concern and work with families to support the safe care of their children.
- Conduct Needs and Risk Assessment and environment scanning to identify needs of the family using tools such as Family and Adult Assessment Tool (FAST) and biopsychosocial approach.
- Participate in formal case reviews and statutory meetings with other partners.
- Conduct systemic casework and counselling to the family unit, and meet the identified caregiver at least once a week to ensure Children have a positive experience of care.
- Implement a range of interventions that strengthen family decision-making and relationships.
- Liaising and Advocating with various stakeholders from community and governmental agencies in mobilizing social and healthcare resources to meet family's needs to ensure children's wellbeing.
- Works with families and other agencies to reduce risk of harm and to support and strengthen families –helping children stay safely with their families where possible.

- Conduct and facilitate case conferences and multi-disciplinary meetings to review the family's progress.
- Design and implement family-based programs to promote family bonding to enhance the permanence factor in the Children's life.
- Maintain a proper and accurate statutory record of the services rendered to family and children and ensure timely submission.

# Social Worker - January 2015 to August 2016 Muslim Missionary Society, Jamiyah Children's Home, Singapore

- Identify and respond to needs and risks to safety, well-being and development of children in care and protection of home.
- Conduct assessment using CANS Framework, planning and intervention for the children's and young people's reintegration to the society as the ultimate objective by involving them.
- Develop and implement a Looking After Children and young people (LAC) Care Plan for each child.
- Provide case management services to children/young people with at-risk and/or school attendanceissues and empower them to lead meaningful and pro-social lifestyles.
- Maintain an up to date knowledge of the development of each child and young person as appropriate.
- Participate in relevant formal and informal Case Plan meetings, Care Team Meetings, professional

Lmeetings and other forums pertaining to the planning and care of the looking after children and young people residing in the home ensuring that the statutory requirements of case management for all cases are met.

- Undertake appropriate case recording, data entry and retrieval in accordance with program procedures, including Family Journey.
- Participate in formal case reviews and statutory meetings with other partners.
- Prepare reports for the Ministry of Social and Family Development (MSF) in relation to allocated cases, where appropriate.
- Work in a therapeutic manner with children and young people and provide guidance and leadership to Residential Care Workers and volunteers around therapeutic care.
- Provide opportunities for and encourage children and young people to invite family members, relatives and friends to the residences as appropriate, as well as to telephone, write and maintain significant contacts in general.
- Liaise with schools, primary caregivers and other community services, prison services and Child Protection, to ensure the well-being and safety of the children and young people.

# Social Worker - April 2013 to September 2013 Guild of Service (Adoption Unit), Chennai. India

- Pre and Post Adoption Counselling to the Adoptive Parents.
- Preparation of reports to be sent to concerned agencies and Documentation of the Adoption data.
- Referral services, Home Visits and Follow up visits.
- Facilitating the legalisation of the adoption by doing the competent court works.
- Liaison with various Government Agencies, Child Welfare Committees, Directorate of Social Welfare and District Social Welfare Office throughout the work period.

# References:

1.Dr. V.A.Vijayaraghavan, Ex Principal Incharge, Madras School of Social Work, Chennai, India Contact No: +91 9444405920 / Email id: <a href="mailto:vav.mssw@gmail.com">vav.mssw@gmail.com</a>

2.Dr H M Saleem, Vice President I, Muslim Missionary Society, Jamiah Children's Home, Singapore Contact No: +65 97831814 / Email id: hmdsaleem@hotmail.com

#### Other Details:

Singapore Association of Social Workers Accreditation validity until 31 December 2019

Singapore Association of Social Workers Membership validity until 31 March 2019

## **DECLARATION**

I hereby declare that all the above furnished details are true to the best of my knowledge and belief.

Sivagami Natarajan(Ms.)